# Joel Worrall

717.385.9970 / joel@joelworrall.com / @tangollama

# Executive Management, Strategic Leadership, Brand Development, Innovation, Technology Product Development, Digital Transformation

## Summary

I started my career in the software industry as a programmer, architect, and consultant. A decade ago, I began growing my skills in the areas of people management, organizational leadership, strategic planning, brand development, product management, and enabling business transformation.

Today, my experiences have equipped me with a team-oriented management philosophy and strategic execution experience at multiple levels combined with a passion the building great technology with great teams. My goal is to invest my skills and management background to provide senior leadership to an organization with a mission I can embrace, a culture I can influence, a team I can pour into, and a vision I can help guide.

### Skills

- Technology product development, including hands-on software engineering and team leadership
- Management of departments across distributed offices, time zones, and continents
- Team leadership, mentoring staff and subordinates, managing up, and coaching peers
- Brand and product development as well as internal and external messaging
- Mass-marketing, messaging, and fundraising, including proposal creation and presentation
- Corporate strategic planning and execution with sustainable results
- Corporate culture leadership, embracing and setting pace for core values
- Personnel management, including restructuring organizational reporting relationships
- Talent identification, recruitment, and onboarding
- Volunteer recruitment and management, including open source software contributors
- Strong presentation, public speaking, and written communication skills
- A track record of creating, influencing and owning a vision for an organization
- Multi-million dollar budget management
- Nearly a decade of Board-level reporting experience
- Formal classroom instruction in a higher education setting

# **Education & Training**

Bachelor's in Computer Science, Messiah College, Grantham, PA (2000)

Master's in Religion, Evangelical Theological Seminary, Myerstown, PA (2015)

The Marketing Seminar with Seth Godin, https://themarketingseminar.com (2017)

## **Presentations & Talks**

See videos of several of my public talks and presentations at <u>joelworrall.com/talks</u>.

# Experience

## New Relic (since May 2018)

New Relic is the industry leader in monitoring and analysis of all layers of the modern cloudstack, adding over two trillion events and metrics per day to their real-time analysis platform while serving over half of the Fortune 100 as well as 17,000 customers. As they bring their next-generation platform to market, my role was created to establish an extensibility practice, working alongside customers to envision and build next-generation real-time monitoring solutions for industries undergoing digital transformation.

#### <u>Principal Extensibility Architect</u> – May 2018 to Present

- Build early-stage and proof-of-concept products on top of the New Relic platform using tools like GraphQL, React, and cloud services
- Helping to deliver and shape New Relic's Developer Program
- Interfacing directly with enterprise customers to envision and instantiate how New Relic's platform can solve real-time business and technology problems
- Representing customer platform needs to New Relic's product teams in Portland and Barcelona
- Representing the goals of the founder/CEO with regards to platform extensibility to the Product,
   Sales, and Services arms of New Relic

Primary technologies / tools: React, Node.js, HTML/CSS/JS, GraphQL, New Relic, GitHub, AWS

## Masterworks (10 months)

Re-platformed a 30-year-old agency that is focused on serving faith-based organizations in the rescue and relief sectors. Masterworks is seeking to reposition itself as a digital leader. In my role, I've helped to reengineer the agency while simultaneously bringing digital products to the market, including a multi-channel data platform aimed at integrating and schematizing offline CRM data, media platforms, and a digital response telemetry.

#### Vice President, Chief Technologist – August 2017 to May 2018

- Creating a data service to aggregate constituent and interaction information across a myriad of
  platforms and disparate tools to create a unified understanding of donor response as well as
  automation models for reacting to constituent actions
- Reshaping technology and digital delivery processes to follow industry best practices
- Building the staffing capabilities of the agency with regards to technology and digital marketing
- Vetting and implementing outsourcing and partner relationships
- Leading platform and partner selection for technology-related systems and solutions
- Supporting the business development of the agency in the areas of strategic planning, IT, program evaluation, and digital marketing
- Serving on the re-branding and marketing committee for the agency

Primary technologies / tools: Google BigQuery, Looker, Piwik Pro, React, Node.js, PHP, Symfony, MySQL, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic, Wordpress, Pantheon, WPEngine, Salesforce.com, Google Apps

## Messiah College (since February 2018)

This is my first, professional teaching engagement as a part-time member of the Computer Science department. After beginning in Spring 2017, I'm currently teaching the senior capstone course for CS.

## CURE International (7.5 years)

Member of the executive leadership team, head of technology, marketing, and CURE's innovative online donor reporting platform (<u>CUREkids</u>), providing oversight and strategic direction to a global charitable healthcare organization with 1,600 employees and an operational presence in 29 countries.

<u>Chief Technology Officer and Office of the CEO</u> – June 2016 to May 2017 <u>Chief Technology Officer</u> – May 2014 to June 2016 <u>Vice President of Technology and Marketing</u> – July 2010 to May 2014 Vice President of Technology – October 2009 to July 2010

- Oversaw all technology, marketing, brand-building and creative efforts
- Served as the lead executive and primary communicator through a CEO transition
- Architected and co-founded the award-winning <u>cure.org</u> and the <u>CUREkids</u> platform
- Co-founded the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source software project
- Led transition from traditional nonprofit software tools to a full cloud technology strategy
- Wrote and spoke for conferences and events across a variety of audiences and venues
- Conducted executive recruiting and management
- Directed crisis communications and public relations
- Directed the creation of CURE's content marketing strategy
- Oversaw the growth of CURE's first, successful monthly recurring revenue program
- Led the messaging and execution for CURE's largest annual fundraising event (\$6M)

Primary technologies / tools: PHP, MySQL, jQuery, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic, Wordpress, Salesforce.com, Google Apps, Mailchimp, Stripe, Hubspot, DigitalOcean, Rackspace

## joelworrall.com (since 2009)

Independent consultant offering technology due diligence, early stage startup technology, marketing, and business development support.

- Providing product focus, technology selection, and branding direction
- Identifying and recruiting technology, marketing, and design talent
- Guiding product and brand direction as well as marketing and PR opportunities
- Supporting initial fundraising through strategic and technical direction

# (Volunteer) HospitalRun (since 2014)

Co-founder of the <u>HospitalRun</u> open source health information platform, responsible for strategic direction, community management, messaging, code contributions, and reviewing pull requests.

Core Team [Volunteer] - February 2014 to July 2018

Primary technologies / tools: Node, Ember, CouchDB, PouchDB, HTML/CSS/JS, GitHub, New Relic

## Mzinga & KnowledgePlanet Inc. (3.5 years)

Led a 75-person engineering department of a venture-backed enterprise software company. Responsible for technology roadmap, product development, acquisition due diligence, and R&D.

<u>Vice President, Engineering & Development</u> – March 2009 to October 2009

<u>Director of Engineering</u> – August 2008 to March 2009

<u>Director of Development, Learning & Workplace Communities</u> – Feb. 2008 to Aug. 2008

<u>Development Manager</u> – Feb. 2007 to Feb. 2008

Software Architect – July 2006 to Jan. 2007

- Led shift of product architecture and business model from Application Service Provider to complete Software as a Service multi-tenant, single instance environment
- Provided technical leadership through a debt restructuring and recapitalization event
- Guided the engineering organization through the merger of three separate companies and development organizations as well as the incorporation of an offshore, outsourced team
- Negotiated major software vendor contracts and services
- Performed technical diligence through acquisitions
- Served as consultant and solution architect, working with troubled client relationships

Primary technologies / tools: Java, HTML/CSS/JS, Oracle, SVN, CVS, FogBugz

## Java Brewery, Inc (3 years)

Outsourced system architecture, software development, and interim engineering management.

Sole Proprietor and Senior Consultant – April 2003 to June 2006

- Engaged in outsourced product development, management, market research, and leadership
- Served as technical liaison and interim engineer for multiple organizations
- Analysis of company models, architecture, requirements, design and implementation services
- Architected the content management tools for Comcast

Primary technologies / tools: Java, MySQL, Postgres, CVS, SVN

## CommNav Inc. (3 years)

Lead Java developer of a 20-person startup focused on a business portal framework.

<u>Lead Architect</u> – July 2000 to April 2003

- Responsible for approving designs and documentation, overseeing and mentoring junior developers, and managing testing for all next-generation product development efforts
- Primary author of the development API's and system documentation

Primary technologies / tools: Java, Postgres, CVS, Bugzilla

## Knowledgeplanet Inc. (1 year)

Entry-level developer that quickly took over leadership in an existing and more senior team.

Software Engineer - May 1999 to June 2000

- Responsible for the installation process and automated testing
- Served as lead on the release of a major architecture change in an enterprise software platform

Primary technologies / tools: Java, Oracle, Microsoft Visual SourceSafe